<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Translation of Giarratano's Preface</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="preface" xml:lang="en">
            <div type="section" n="1">
               <head>I</head>
               <p>The seven eclogues of Calpurnius and the four of Nemesianus are preserved in the
                  same manuscripts, which is how it happens that they are always published together
                  by scholar, even though they differ in terms of refinement and charm. Add to this
                  the fact that many who use inferior manuscripts that attribute the eleven eclogues
                  to Calpurnius alone say that Nemesianus did not write any eclogues. From the time
                  of [Taddeo] Ugoleto there has been no lack of those who divide the poems between
                  Calpurnius and Nemesianus, assigning the last four to the latter, but until
                  recently they thought that Calpurnius had sent his poems to Nemesianus. But
                        <bibl><author>Moriz Haupt</author> (<title xml:lang="la"><hi rend="italic"
                              ><ref
                              target="https://books.google.com/books?id=Z-8nAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"
                              >De Carminibus bucolicis Calpurnii et Nemesiani</ref></hi></title>,
                        <pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>, <date>1854</date>, <biblScope unit="page">p.
                        1–27</biblScope>)</bibl> demonstrated with ample and reliable evidence that
                  those eleven eclogues belong neither to one poet nor to the same period, but
                  rather that the first seven should be assigned to Calpurnius and the rest to
                  Nemesianus. He also demonstrated that Calpurnius lived under the reign of Nero,
                  but Nemesianus lived in the time of Carus and his sons. Haupt's opinion, which
                        <bibl><author>Kraffert</author> (<title xml:lang="de"><hi rend="italic"
                           >Beitr. zur Kritik und Erklaerung lat. Autoren</hi></title>
                     <biblScope unit="volume">T. 3</biblScope>, <pubPlace>Aurich</pubPlace>
                     <date>1883</date>, <biblScope unit="page">p. 151</biblScope>)</bibl> et
                        <bibl><author>Garnett</author> (<title level="a">On the date of Calp.
                        Sic.</title>, <title level="j">Journ. of philol.</title>
                     <biblScope unit="volume">XVI</biblScope>
                     <date>1888</date>
                     <biblScope unit="page">p. 216</biblScope></bibl>, cfr. <bibl><author>J. P.
                        Postgate</author>, <title level="a">The comet of Calpurnius Siculus</title>,
                        <title level="j">Class. Rev.</title>
                     <date>1902</date>
                     <biblScope unit="page">p. 38–40</biblScope></bibl>) have recently argued
                  against in vain, now deservedly has the greatest authority among scholars.
                  Nevertheless, both because of the similarity in subject matter and the fact that
                  the condition of the text is the same in both poets' eclogues, I prefer to place
                  Calpurnius side-by-side with Nemesianus.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>There are three closely related families of manuscripts of Calpurnius and
                  Nemesianus, in particular all of those that trace their origin back to three books
                  copied from the same archetype. The first family includes two manuscripts that
                  should be considered the best witnesses of all, since they are nearly free of
                  interpolations, even though they rather frequently show blemishes from the
                  ignorance and carelessness of their copyists. Many manuscripts conform to the
                  so-called family <ref target="#V">V</ref>. Their extraordinary agreement in many
                  errors demonstrates that all of them emanate from one book, which is also clear
                  enough from the sheer abundance of interpolations that are unique to this family.
                  And yet, these manuscripts are not corrupted in the same manner, but they can be
                  divided into distinct groups, which seems to me a tedious business and hardly
                  worthwhile. Besides, <bibl><author>Schenkl</author> (<title level="j">Wiener
                        Studien</title>
                     <biblScope unit="volume">V</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="page">p. 294 sqq.</biblScope>
                     <date>1883</date></bibl> and on page 50ff. of the preface to his first edition
                  ) has distinguished two families, <hi rend="italic">v</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                     >w</hi>, but I wish he had not. It is easy for me to agree with that most
                  learned man concerning the group that is called <hi rend="italic">w</hi>; but with
                  regard to the manuscripts that he denotes with the letter <hi rend="italic"
                  >v</hi>, it is impossible to know that all of them are of the same kind when only
                  a few readings have been received full scrutiny. But one manuscript is assigned to
                  the third family because it presents very many errors that the other manuscripts
                  lack entirely. Moreover, a good number of readings are found in it that are
                  characteristic of the better manuscripts, but it has none in common with the
                  inferior manuscripts. For this reason it occupies a kind of middle ground, so to
                  speak, between the books of good repute and those that have been corrupted.
                  Indeed, readings have been selected for these books from the German manuscript of
                  Thadeus Ugoletus and from the manuscript belonging to Boccaccio, and various
                  excerpts should be added, too. I will consider these matters below.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>Now it is necessary to discuss the manuscripts of the first family: <ref
                     target="#N">N = Neapolitanus V a 8</ref> and <ref target="#G">G = Gaddianus
                     Laur. plut. 90, 12 inf.</ref></p>
               <p>Codex Neapolitanus V a 8, formerly 280, parchment, 0.261 X 0.160 cm., written at
                  about the beginning of the fifteenth century. It consists of 116 folios, of which
                  1–36a contain Cato's <hi rend="italic">De Agricultura</hi>; 20–101a, Varro's <hi
                     rend="italic">De Re Rustica</hi>; 101a–115b, the <hi rend="italic">Bucolic</hi>
                  of Calpurnius and Nemesianus. The remaining folios are blank. Each page has
                  thirty-eight verses. With respect to correcting hands, the manuscript put two in
                  particular to the test. The first belongs to the original copyist. The manuscript
                  was corrected again around the same time, but here and there the second hand
                  cannot easily be distinguished from the first. A third hand's emendations can be
                  discerned in only a few places. The individual poems lack titles, but they are
                  separated from each other by brief spaces. The following subscription appears at
                  the end of the whole work: <hi rend="italic">Aureliani Nemesiani Cartag&#773;
                     bucol&#8217; explicit: Deo gratias amen</hi>. Finally, another more recent
                  hand, as Bursian and Schenkl recognized, wrote <hi rend="italic">Calpurnii
                     eclogae</hi> et <hi rend="italic">Nemesiani eclogae</hi>.</p>
               <p>We know nothing about the origin and provenance of this manuscript except what is
                  understood from the following passages written on the last folio: "Joannes
                  Antonius Perillus, a nobleman of Naples and most learned gentleman, gave this book
                  to Jacob Perillus in 1667 on the first of June," and a little below, "This book
                  belongs to Antonius Seripandus, received as a gift from his best friend Jacob
                  Perillus." Later it was brought to the library of San Giovanni a Carbonara, and
                  from there it came to the greatest library in Naples, formerly known as the
                     <orgName xml:id="preface-borbonica">Reale biblioteca borbonica</orgName><note
                     target="#preface-borbonica">Now the <orgName ref="http://www.bnnonline.it"
                        >Biblioteca nazionale Vittorio Emanuele III</orgName></note>.
                     <persName>Jacques Philippe D'Orville</persName> was the first to collate this
                  manuscript carefully enough for <persName>Pieter Burmann's</persName> use; his
                  collation appears in the <ref
                     target="https://books.google.be/books?id=fSIPAAAAQAAJ&amp;hl=nl&amp;pg=PA723#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"
                     >appendix</ref> to <bibl><author>Burman's</author>
                     <title corresp="#Burm">Poetae Latini Minores</title>
                     <biblScope unit="volume">Vol. 1</biblScope></bibl>. Next, <persName>Conrad
                     Bursian</persName> examined it on behalf of <persName>Moriz Haupt</persName>,
                  but nothing is known about the worth of his collation, since the edition promissed
                  by Haupt was never published. <persName>Baehrens</persName> was the next to use
                  it, but in way that rightly earned the scorn of <persName>Schenkl</persName>, who
                  collated the manuscript in 1878 and inspected it again a few years later when
                  preparing his <ref target="#Schenkl2">second edition of Calpurnius and
                     Nemesianus</ref>. For my part, I examined the entire manuscript in 1907, but to
                  remove all of the discrepancies between my collation and the testimony of Schenkl,
                  in the summer of 1909 my friend <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/311005886"
                     >Giampietro Zottoli</persName> inspected with me all of the places where
                  <persName>Schenkl</persName> had a different reading, and we often uncovered carelessness on <persName>Schenkl</persName>'s
                  part. I have published in my apparatus criticus the entire collation of his
                  manuscript, omitting not even the slightest thing to do with orthography.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p>Some text here.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
