<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Translation of Giarratano's Preface</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="preface" xml:lang="en">
            <div type="section" n="1">
               <head>I: Calpurnius and Nemesianus</head>
               <p>The seven eclogues of Calpurnius and the four of Nemesianus are preserved in the
                  same manuscripts, which is how it happens that they are always published together
                  by scholar, even though they differ in terms of refinement and charm. Add to this
                  the fact that many who use inferior manuscripts that attribute the eleven eclogues
                  to Calpurnius alone say that Nemesianus did not write any eclogues. From the time
                  of [Taddeo] Ugoleto there has been no lack of those who divide the poems between
                  Calpurnius and Nemesianus, assigning the last four to the latter, but until
                  recently they thought that Calpurnius had sent his poems to Nemesianus. But
                        <bibl><author>Moriz Haupt</author> (<title xml:lang="la"><hi rend="italic"
                              ><ref
                              target="https://books.google.com/books?id=Z-8nAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"
                              >De Carminibus bucolicis Calpurnii et Nemesiani</ref></hi></title>,
                        <pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>, <date>1854</date>, <biblScope unit="page">p.
                        1–27</biblScope>)</bibl> demonstrated with ample and reliable evidence that
                  those eleven eclogues belong neither to one poet nor to the same period, but
                  rather that the first seven should be assigned to Calpurnius and the rest to
                  Nemesianus. He also demonstrated that Calpurnius lived under the reign of Nero,
                  but Nemesianus lived in the time of Carus and his sons. Haupt's opinion, which
                        <bibl><author>Kraffert</author> (<title xml:lang="de"><hi rend="italic"
                           >Beitr. zur Kritik und Erklaerung lat. Autoren</hi></title>
                     <biblScope unit="volume">T. 3</biblScope>, <pubPlace>Aurich</pubPlace>
                     <date>1883</date>, <biblScope unit="page">p. 151</biblScope>)</bibl> et
                        <bibl><author>Garnett</author> (<title level="a">On the date of Calp.
                        Sic.</title>, <title level="j">Journ. of philol.</title>
                     <biblScope unit="volume">XVI</biblScope>
                     <date>1888</date>
                     <biblScope unit="page">p. 216</biblScope></bibl>, cfr. <bibl><author>J. P.
                        Postgate</author>, <title level="a">The comet of Calpurnius Siculus</title>,
                        <title level="j">Class. Rev.</title>
                     <date>1902</date>
                     <biblScope unit="page">p. 38–40</biblScope></bibl>) have recently argued
                  against in vain, now deservedly has the greatest authority among scholars.
                  Nevertheless, both because of the similarity in subject matter and the fact that
                  the condition of the text is the same in both poets' eclogues, I prefer to place
                  Calpurnius side-by-side with Nemesianus.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
               <head>II. Overview of the Manuscript Tradition</head>
               <p>There are three closely related families of manuscripts of Calpurnius and
                  Nemesianus, in particular all of those that trace their origin back to three books
                  copied from the same archetype. The first family includes two manuscripts that
                  should be considered the best witnesses of all, since they are nearly free of
                  interpolations, even though they rather frequently show blemishes from the
                  ignorance and carelessness of their copyists. Many manuscripts conform to the
                  so-called family <ref target="#V">V</ref>. Their extraordinary agreement in many
                  errors demonstrates that all of them emanate from one book, which is also clear
                  enough from the sheer abundance of interpolations that are unique to this family.
                  And yet, these manuscripts are not corrupted in the same manner, but they can be
                  divided into distinct groups, which seems to me a tedious business and hardly
                  worthwhile. Besides, <bibl><author>Schenkl</author> (<title level="j">Wiener
                        Studien</title>
                     <biblScope unit="volume">V</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="page">p. 294 sqq.</biblScope>
                     <date>1883</date></bibl> and on page 50ff. of the preface to his first edition
                  ) has distinguished two families, <hi rend="italic">v</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                     >w</hi>, but I wish he had not. It is easy for me to agree with that most
                  learned man concerning the group that is called <hi rend="italic">w</hi>; but with
                  regard to the manuscripts that he denotes with the letter <hi rend="italic"
                  >v</hi>, it is impossible to know that all of them are of the same kind when only
                  a few readings have been received full scrutiny. But one manuscript is assigned to
                  the third family because it presents very many errors that the other manuscripts
                  lack entirely. Moreover, a good number of readings are found in it that are
                  characteristic of the better manuscripts, but it has none in common with the
                  inferior manuscripts. For this reason it occupies a kind of middle ground, so to
                  speak, between the books of good repute and those that have been corrupted.
                  Indeed, readings have been selected for these books from the German manuscript of
                  Thadeus Ugoletus and from the manuscript belonging to Boccaccio, and various
                  excerpts should be added, too. I will consider these matters below.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
               <head>III. The First Family: N and G</head>
               <p>Now it is necessary to discuss the manuscripts of the first family: <ref
                     target="#N">N = Neapolitanus V a 8</ref> and <ref target="#G">G = Gaddianus
                     Laur. plut. 90, 12 inf.</ref></p>
               <p>Codex Neapolitanus V a 8, formerly 280, parchment, 0.261 X 0.160 cm., written at
                  about the beginning of the fifteenth century. It consists of 116 folios, of which
                  1–36a contain Cato's <hi rend="italic">De Agricultura</hi>; 20–101a, Varro's <hi
                     rend="italic">De Re Rustica</hi>; 101a–115b, the <hi rend="italic">Bucolic</hi>
                  of Calpurnius and Nemesianus. The remaining folios are blank. Each page has
                  thirty-eight verses. With respect to correcting hands, the manuscript put two in
                  particular to the test. The first belongs to the original copyist. The manuscript
                  was corrected again around the same time, but here and there the second hand
                  cannot easily be distinguished from the first. A third hand's emendations can be
                  discerned in only a few places. The individual poems lack titles, but they are
                  separated from each other by brief spaces. The following subscription appears at
                  the end of the whole work: <hi rend="italic">Aureliani Nemesiani Cartag&#773;
                     bucol&#8217; explicit: Deo gratias amen</hi>. Finally, another more recent
                  hand, as Bursian and Schenkl recognized, wrote <hi rend="italic">Calpurnii
                     eclogae</hi> et <hi rend="italic">Nemesiani eclogae</hi>.</p>
               <p>We know nothing about the origin and provenance of this manuscript except what is
                  understood from the following passages written on the last folio: "Joannes
                  Antonius Perillus, a nobleman of Naples and most learned gentleman, gave this book
                  to Jacob Perillus in 1667 on the first of June," and a little below, "This book
                  belongs to Antonius Seripandus, received as a gift from his best friend Jacob
                  Perillus." Later it was brought to the library of San Giovanni a Carbonara, and
                  from there it came to the greatest library in Naples, formerly known as the
                     <orgName xml:id="preface-borbonica">Reale biblioteca borbonica</orgName><note
                     target="#preface-borbonica">Now the <orgName ref="http://www.bnnonline.it"
                        >Biblioteca nazionale Vittorio Emanuele III</orgName></note>.
                     <persName>Jacques Philippe D'Orville</persName> was the first to collate this
                  manuscript carefully enough for <persName>Pieter Burmann's</persName> use; his
                  collation appears in the <ref
                     target="https://books.google.be/books?id=fSIPAAAAQAAJ&amp;hl=nl&amp;pg=PA723#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"
                     >appendix</ref> to <bibl><author>Burman's</author>
                     <title corresp="#Burm">Poetae Latini Minores</title>
                     <biblScope unit="volume">Vol. 1</biblScope></bibl>. Next, <persName>Conrad
                     Bursian</persName> examined it on behalf of <persName>Moriz Haupt</persName>,
                  but nothing is known about the worth of his collation, since the edition promissed
                  by Haupt was never published. <persName>Baehrens</persName> was the next to use
                  it, but in way that rightly earned the scorn of <persName>Schenkl</persName>, who
                  collated the manuscript in 1878 and inspected it again a few years later when
                  preparing his <ref target="#Schenkl2">second edition of Calpurnius and
                     Nemesianus</ref>. For my part, I examined the entire manuscript in 1907, but to
                  remove all of the discrepancies between my collation and the testimony of Schenkl,
                  in the summer of 1909 my friend <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/311005886"
                     >Giampietro Zottoli</persName> inspected with me all of the places where
                     <persName>Schenkl</persName> had a different reading, and we often uncovered
                  carelessness on <persName>Schenkl</persName>'s part. I have published in my
                  apparatus criticus the entire collation of his manuscript, omitting not even the
                  slightest thing to do with orthography.</p>
               <p>Codex Gaddianus Laurentianus plut. 90, 12 inf., paper, 0.294 X 0.225 cm, written
                  at the beginning of the fifteenth century, consists of 74 folios. It contains the
                  twelve eclogues of Francesco Petrarch (ff. 1–44), the
                     <bibl><title>Culex</title></bibl> of Vergilius Maro, the
                        <bibl><title>Dirae</title></bibl> of Vergilius Maro (ff. 52–55), and
                  Calpurnius and Nemesianus (ff. 55–74). A very brief, unattributed ecloque follows
                  with the interlocutors Daphnis, Tityrus, Mopsus, and
                  Meliboeus<!-- should these be encoded with <persName>? -->. Individual pages
                  generally have twenty-nine versus, but some vary, with the shorter ones having
                  twenty-six and the longer ones haveing thirty-two verses. The following
                  inscription has been added to the eclogues of Calpurnius: <quote>The Eclogues of
                     Calfurnius to Nemesianus of Carthage</quote>. Nemesianus follows Calpurnius
                  with the following title prefixed: <quote>Here begin the eclogues of Aurelianus
                     Nemesianus of Carthage</quote>. At the end of each eclogue there appears an <hi
                     rend="italic">explicit</hi> with the number of each eclogue, but Calpunrius'
                  sixth eclogue lacks a subscription, and the following is written at the end of the
                  seventh: <quote>Here ends the sixth eclogue of Calphurnius</quote>. This is
                  explained by the fact that the seventh eclogue follows the sixth without any
                  break, with the result that only six eclogues are attributed to Calpurnius in this
                  manuscript. But in the margin, where the sixth eclogue ought to end, the copyist
                  has added the following: <quote>Some wish to say that the eclogue that begins <hi
                        rend="italic">lentus</hi> is a completely different eclogue; others say that
                     it is the same, etc.</quote></p>
               <p>In this manuscript the copyist himself added almost all of the corrections either
                  by removing scribal errors in the verses or adding variant readings to the margin.
                  But there are some that seem to have been made by another hand. The manuscript was
                  mentioned by <bibl><editor><ref target="#Glaeser">Glaeser</ref></editor></bibl>
                  and <bibl><author><ref target="#Haupt">Haupt</ref></author></bibl>, but
                           <bibl><editor><ref target="#Baehr.">Baehrens</ref></editor></bibl> was
                  the first to examine it, far too hurriedly; <bibl><editor><ref target="#Schenkl"
                           >Schenkl</ref></editor></bibl> was the next to use it, much more
                  carefully. I myself transcribed the manuscript in 1908 with as much attentiveness
                  as I could, but I collated it again in the following year, to settle all of the
                  discrepancies with <ref target="#Schenkl">Schenkl</ref>. Still, there are very
                  many places that <ref target="Schenkl">Schenkl</ref> has reported erroneously, as
                  you can gather from my notes, for I have taken greatest pains to publish all of
                  the readings of this manuscript, too.</p>
               <p>Having described the outer appearance of manuscripts N and G and explained their
                  provenance, I must now discuss in more detail their relationship and their
                  importance. Until now, no one except Baehrens and Schenkl has examined the
                  authority of either manuscript. It is no wonder, since Baehrens was the first to
                  collate the Gaddianus, and no one before Glaeser considered the Neapolitanus of
                  much value. But Baehrens and Schenkl held different opinions: the former, as
                  usual, overvalues the manuscript that he was the first to publish and argues that
                  the Gaddianus is superior to the others; the latter, however, prefers the
                  Neapolitanus. But Baehrens asserts his point of view instead of demonstrating it
                  with strong evidence. On the other hand, Schenkl tried to demonstrate that the
                  Gaddianus admitted interpolations in some places. It seems to me that neither one
                  has hit upon the truth entirely, as I think the following makes clear.</p>
               <p>I have already said that both manuscripts descend from the same archetype, and
                  that is supported by the very large number of readings that N has in common with
                  G, when something else is written in the rest of the manuscripts. But, to be fair,
                  they differ among themselves in many places, and it is right to discuss their
                  differences so that it will be easier to see which manuscript departs less from
                  the archetype. In doing this, I take no account of readings that are attributed to
                  the second or third hand in the Neapolitanus or of the various readings that the
                  copyist added in the margin of the Gaddianus. I shall consider them later.</p>
               <p>But first of all, although the repute of each of the two manuscripts is frequently
                  distorted because of the carelessness and ignorance of the copyists, it seems to
                  me that the Gaddianus was copied a little more carelessly. For instance, four
                  verses (C. 1.40, 4.16, 4.123; N. 1.73) are missing from it, and Nemesianus 2.49
                  has been placed after verse 45: Moreover, the following words have been omitted:
                  C. 1.92 <quote>ipsa</quote>, 2.88 <quote>quotiens</quote>, 3.23
                     <quote>deus</quote>, 3.3 <quote>sed</quote>, 3.89 <quote>non</quote>. But in
                  the Neapolitan manuscript, no verse is missing (it is unnecessary, I think, for me
                  to remind you that I speak here about the unique defects of each manuscript, not
                  about the common defects that are rightly assigned to the archetype), but C.
                  1.31–32 have been inverted and N. 2.81 were inserted after 3.16. Then the copyist
                  overlooked the following words: C. 6.46 <quote>pignus</quote>, 6.90
                     <quote>hoc</quote>, N. 1.23 <quote>et</quote>, 1.71 <quote>et</quote>, 3.5
                     <quote>ex tereti</quote>, 4.60 <quote>audit</quote>. Add to this the fact that
                  in almost 130 places N offers the correct reading and G an erroneous one, and the
                  opposite happens a little less frequently.</p>
               <p>Each of the two manuscripts has some errors (N has more by far) in common with V,
                  which could not have happened always entirely by chance. The following places are
                  clearly due to interpolation: C. 2.73 <quote>cicius</quote> or <quote>citius
                     tenues</quote> NV, 3.35 <quote>quod</quote> NV, 6.25 <quote>verba</quote> N,
                     <quote>verba</quote> and <quote>verbo</quote> V, 6.82 <quote>te stante</quote>
                  NV, 7.33 <quote>tibi</quote> GV, N. 3.37 <quote>ostendit</quote>. The rest of the
                  examples are either doubtful or should be disregarded entirely.</p>
               <p>Next, some have deemed the following places in G as possibly
                  suspicious:<!-- Maybe do this as a list? --> C I 12 <quote>errantes</quote>, 85
                     <quote>accipiet</quote>, III 20 <quote>invenias</quote>, IV 2
                     <quote>obstrepit</quote>, 53 <quote>discere</quote>, 72
                     <quote>aspernatur</quote>, 85 <quote>corpore</quote>, 105 <quote>enim</quote>,
                  150 <quote>liquide</quote>, V 31 <quote>primum</quote>, 44 <quote>pascua</quote>,
                  52, <quote>quod</quote>, VI 59 <quote>mascillo</quote>, VII 11
                     <quote>herus</quote>, 26 <quote>in</quote>, 41 <quote>non</quote>, N. I 2
                     <quote>raris</quote>, 5 <quote>flavit</quote>, 16 <quote>carmina</quote>, 63
                     <quote>carmina</quote>, 82 <quote>canis</quote>, II 27 <quote>nostri
                     tamquam</quote>, 32 <quote>ethera</quote>, 74 <quote>omnes</quote>, 89
                     <quote>discedere</quote>, III 52 <quote>saliensque liquore</quote>. But
                     <quote>enim</quote>, <quote>pascua</quote>, <quote>mascillo</quote>,
                     <quote>in</quote>, <quote>canis</quote> are without doubt glosses inserted
                  later in place of the poets' words. One could say the same thing about
                     <quote>accipiet</quote>, <quote>ethera</quote>, <quote>discedere</quote>. Also
                     <quote>aethera</quote> and <quote>discedere</quote> are just as good as
                     <quote>aera</quote> and <quote>descendere</quote>, and for a long time I was
                  not sure which of the two I preferred. And <quote>liquide</quote>,
                     <quote>primum</quote>, <quote>flavit</quote>, <quote>carmina</quote> (N. I 16)
                  should not be considered interpolations, but rather corruptions that arose in
                  these places since the words that should have been written by the copyist appeared
                  nearby. Thus, <quote>liquide</quote> is derived from <quote>dulce</quote>,
                     <quote>primum</quote> from <quote>spatium</quote>, <quote>flavit</quote> from
                     <quote>inflare</quote>, <quote>carmina</quote> from <quote>carmine</quote>. But
                     <quote>carmina</quote> (N. 1.63) is either a gloss or a corruption that owes
                  its origin from the initial sound of the next word, and <quote>corpore</quote> and
                     <quote>robore</quote> are very often confused in the manuscripts. Then there
                  are these words: <quote>herus</quote>, <quote>raris</quote>, <quote>omnes</quote>.
                  One would hardly believe that they were made by an interpolator since they do are
                  meaningless. But for the most part, the rest of the examples can be attributed to
                  an interpolator. The following places in N should be considered: C. 1.13
                     <quote>sequar</quote>, 4.46 <quote>inter nostras</quote>, 4.136 <quote>pede
                     velox</quote>, 4.153 <quote>in</quote>, 4.164 <quote>vestros</quote>, N. 2.71
                     <quote>ducas</quote>. <quote>in</quote> is a gloss. <quote>ducas</quote> is
                  closer to <quote>ducam</quote>, which the inferior manuscripts have, than to
                     <quote>duco</quote>, which G correctly offers. <quote>vestros</quote> is owed
                  to an interpolator. The rest are uncertain.</p>
               <p>Finally, the writings of both manuscripts have been corrupted in various was, but
                  sometimes they betray an infelicitous effort at emendation. I would like you to
                  consider the following places, for it is not necessary to say anything about the
                  rest): C. 1.90 <quote>querit</quote> N, <quote>petit</quote> G; 2.96
                     <quote>o</quote> G; 3.50 <quote>turbidus</quote> G; 4.63 <quote>carmen
                     modulavit</quote> G; 4.125 <quote>placanda</quote> G; 5.15
                     <quote>montibus</quote> G; 5.16 <quote>cecinere</quote> G; 5.104
                     <quote>nectendum</quote> N, <quote>videndum</quote> G; N. 2.30 <quote>nullo
                     sudarunt</quote> G, 4.28 <quote>volucrum tum</quote> G; 4.39
                     <quote>subeunte</quote> G. Indeed it is hardly the case that all of these
                  places are equally suspicious, for <quote>o</quote> is a gloss, and I do not think
                  one should think otherwise about <quote>carmen modulavit</quote>. But
                     <quote>turbidus</quote> is clearly an interpolation, which I could hardly say
                  about <quote>volucrum tum</quote>. Then <quote>querit</quote> and
                     <quote>petit</quote> perhaps stem from a poorly understood abbreviation of the
                  word <quote>quatit</quote>, but that gives me pause. But the other examples, with
                  due respect to Schenkl, are hardly attributable to interpolators, unless you
                  happen to think that those interpolators were completely ignorant of the Latin
                  language.</p>
               <p>But before we pass judgment on the authority of manuscripts N and G, we must say a
                  few things about the corrections that each manuscript underwent.</p>
               <p>Manuscript N, as we said above, was emended rather often by the original copyist
                  and others. But all of the emendations of the first hand, which I have detected in
                  almost sixty places, arose from the archetype itself. The copyist, as often
                  happens, sometimes corrected the more trivial scribal errors as he wrote; we are
                  all used to making these errors when we write. Accordingly, he added letters that
                  he omitted by writing too quickly, or he delected extra letters, or he changed
                  vowels and consonants, or he added words that had been omitted, or he restored the
                  order of verses, or he inserted notes about people. Since that is the case, nearly
                  all of the emendations by the first hand are good, or, to state it more
                  truthfully, they restore the wording of the archetype. At C. 1.20, the first hand
                  corrected <quote>dipicta</quote> to <quote>depicta</quote>, which <ref
                     target="#Jacoby">Jacoby</ref> recently defended in vain, since
                     <quote>descripta</quote> is to be read without doubt (cfr. Verg. Ecl. 5.13 and
                  Calp. 1.25), but <quote>depicta</quote> was in the archetype, as G shows us.
                  Similarly at N. 4.65 <quote>aversa</quote> is wrong (cfr. Verg. Ecl. 8.101 sq.),
                  and the first hand has changed the fault into <quote>adversa</quote>, but
                     <quote>adversa</quote> is found in G, from which you can easily conclude that
                  the same reading appeared in the archetype. Only once did the first hand corrupt
                  the true reading of the archetype (C. 3.67 <quote>qui</quote> from
                     <quote>quam</quote>), but that should be attributed to an abbreviation, not at
                  all to his intellect. Finally, all of the corrections of the first hand are
                  confirmed by the readings in manuscript G, with the exception of C. 1.24
                     <quote>propius</quote>, where I have reasonable suspicion that the person who
                  wrote G misread the word.</p>
               <p>The second hand's so-called emendations are three times as frequent as the first
                  hand's, but in terms of proportion, they are found much more often in Calpurnius
                  than in Nemesianus, and around a third of them are correct. For the most part, the
                  second hand corrects scribal errors of a more trivial sort, but sometimes it
                  restores omitted verses or errors, or it corrects transposed verses, or it
                  completely overhauls more serious problems. In general, the second hand's
                  emendations come from manuscripts of the second family, not the archetype, but an
                  interpolator has corrected some of them after his own fashion. It does not take
                  many examples to demonstrate this, but, to begin with passages successfully
                  restored, consider these readings with me, dear reader:</p>
               <table rows="18" cols="3">
                  <head>Comparison of N¹ and G with N² and V</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Line</cell>
                     <cell>N¹ and G</cell>
                     <cell>N²V</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1.20</cell>
                     <cell><quote>depicta</quote> N (ex <quote>dipicta</quote>) G</cell>
                     <cell><quote>descripta</quote></cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1.25</cell>
                     <cell><quote>codice</quote></cell>
                     <cell><quote>cortice</quote></cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1.42</cell>
                     <cell>omitted</cell>
                     <cell>added</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1.55</cell>
                     <cell><quote>profuso</quote></cell>
                     <cell><quote>professo</quote> (and many other mss.)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1.87</cell>
                     <cell><quote>a</quote></cell>
                     <cell><quote>ex</quote> (and many other mss.)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3.26</cell>
                     <cell><quote>ibi</quote></cell>
                     <cell><quote>sibi</quote></cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4.12</cell>
                     <cell><quote>C.</quote> omitted</cell>
                     <cell><quote>C.</quote> added</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4.46</cell>
                     <cell><quote>quicquam</quote></cell>
                     <cell>quisquam</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4.82</cell>
                     <cell><quote>canat</quote></cell>
                     <cell>canit</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4.124</cell>
                     <cell><quote>raptas</quote></cell>
                     <cell><quote>ruptas</quote></cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4.145</cell>
                     <cell><quote>nos</quote></cell>
                     <cell><quote>hos</quote></cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5.7</cell>
                     <cell>entire line placed before line 6</cell>
                     <cell>corrected</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5.28</cell>
                     <cell><quote>vivat</quote></cell>
                     <cell><quote>vivit</quote></cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5.45</cell>
                     <cell><quote>peragunt</quote></cell>
                     <cell><quote>peragit</quote></cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>7.48</cell>
                     <cell><quote>tibi</quote></cell>
                     <cell><quote>ubi</quote></cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>N. 2.50</cell>
                     <cell><quote>cum</quote></cell>
                     <cell><quote>dum</quote></cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3.6</cell>
                     <cell><quote>h</quote>N, om. G</cell>
                     <cell><quote>hanc pueri tamquam</quote></cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>On the other hand, an interpolator has cleverly emended the following:C. 3.91
                     <quote>licidan</quote> N², <quote>licidax</quote> N, <quote>licidas</quote> or
                     <quote>lycidas</quote> G V, 4.152 <quote>teriti</quote> N G,
                     <quote>tereti</quote> N².</p>
               <p>Do it not seem to you that I have demonstrated what I set out to prove? Or does it
                  seem likely that N and G corrupted the good readings of the archetype in the same
                  way in all of these places? But, is you need more proof, reflect on these other
                  examples. First of all, in following places the second hand of manuscript N
                  substituted the interpolations that mar the manuscripts in V for the genuine
                  readings of the archetype: C. 2.8 <quote>vindicet</quote>* (I have indicated all
                  correct reading with an asterisk) N G, <quote>vendicet</quote> N²V; 2.9
                     <quote>thyrsi</quote>*, <quote>tyrsi</quote> G, <quote>tirsi</quote> N,
                     <quote>tirso</quote> N²V pler.; 4.42 <quote>baetis</quote>*,
                     <quote>bethis</quote> G, <quote>beris</quote> N, <quote>bactrus</quote> N²V;
                  4.53 <quote>tantum-ventos</quote>* N G, <quote>solum-nimbos</quote> N²V pler.;
                  4.75 <quote>quam</quote>* G, <quote>q&#773;m</quote> N, <quote>qua</quote> N²V
                  nonn.; 4.131 <quote>iam surdant</quote>* G, <quote>iam surdat</quote> N,
                     <quote>exsurdant</quote> N²V nonn.; 4.148 <quote>deas</quote>* G
                     (<quote>deas</quote> = <hi rend="italic">Musas</hi>, as <ref target="#Leo">F.
                     Leo</ref> demonstrated), <quote>d'as</quote> N, <quote>deos</quote> N²V; 5.49
                     <quote>afferet</quote>* N G, <quote>afferat</quote> N²V nonn.; 5.61
                     <quote>serique-premendi</quote>* N G, <quote>seraeque-merendae</quote> N²V;
                  5.97 <quote>circitor</quote>* N G, <quote>vinitor</quote> N²V; 5.99
                     <quote>nunc</quote>* N G, <quote>tunc</quote> N²V; 6.47 <quote>perdere</quote>*
                  N, <quote>prodere</quote> G, <quote>pendere</quote> N²V; 6.75 <quote>illis</quote>
                  N G, <quote>ipsi</quote> N²V, pler.; N 1.27 <quote>laudem</quote>* N G,
                     <quote>musam</quote> N²V; 1.54 <quote>iuris</quote>* N G, <quote>iusti</quote>
                  N²V; 2.28 <quote>nostros posset</quote>* N G, <quote>posset rapidos</quote> N²V
                  pler.; 4.66 <quote>urar</quote>* N, <quote>uror</quote> G, <quote>arsi</quote>
                  N²V; cfr praeterea 4.63 <quote>carmen modulabile</quote> N²V nonn., which Baehrens
                  would not have received into the text, if he had assessed carefully the things
                  Haupt discussed about elisions in Calpurnius, and 5.65 <quote>coagulat
                     lacte</quote> N², which clearly comes from <quote>coagula lactis</quote> V.
                  Next, in the following places the second hand made some very poor attempts at
                  conjectures for words handed down in the tradition: C. 1.31
                  <quote>sequaci</quote>* G, <quote>sagaci</quote> N²; 1.73 <quote>auferet</quote>*
                  N G, <quote>afferet</quote> N²; 1.85 <quote>excipiet</quote>* N,
                     <quote>excuciet</quote> N²; 2.76 <quote>herbas</quote>* N G,
                     <quote>uvas</quote> N²; 3.25 <quote>sprevi</quote>* G,
                     <quote>spiritu&#773;</quote> N, <quote>speciem</quote> N²; 3.46
                     <quote>acerba</quote>* N G, <quote>avena</quote> N²; 4.79
                     <quote>succinet</quote>*, <quote>subcinit</quote> G, <quote>succinit</quote> N,
                     <quote>sucinat</quote> N²; 4.106 <quote>palen</quote>*, <quote>panem</quote> N
                  G, <quote>palam</quote> N²; 4.111 <quote>densat</quote>* G, <quote>pensat</quote>
                  N, <quote>pulsat</quote> N²; 4.121 <quote>et</quote>* N G, <quote>at</quote> N²;
                  4.124 <quote>saliat</quote>*, <quote>psallat</quote> G, <quote>psalat</quote> N,
                     <quote>psaliat</quote> N²; 5.27 <quote>voca</quote>* N G, <quote>loca</quote>
                  N²; 6.19 <quote>vis</quote>* N G, <quote>visne</quote> N²; 6.37
                     <quote>fruticat</quote>*, <quote>fruticet</quote> G, <quote>frutiō</quote> N,
                     <quote>fruticem</quote> N²; 6.69 <quote>mutavimus</quote>* N G,
                     <quote>mutuabimus</quote> N²; N. 1.1 <quote>fiscella</quote>* N G,
                     <quote>cistella</quote> N², 1.5 <quote>versuque</quote>* N G,
                     <quote>versusque</quote> N²; 2.17 <quote>leves</quote>* N G,
                     <quote>lenes</quote> N².</p>
               <p>And so if the second hand's emendations agree with manuscripts of family V, they
                  can add no authority to them, since they arose from them; but if they depend on no
                  other book, they must be considered to be the conjectures of a fairly learned
                  person. If we have discussed them correctly, the emendations of that sort are
                  entirely without merit, and I did not unjustly omit them outright when I compared
                  manuscript N with G.</p>
               <p>Finally, there are five emendations by the third hand, of which three are good (C.
                  2.1 puer, 2.4 gravis, 2.33 pomona) and two are bad (C. 1.59 truderit, 5.11
                  ganā).</p>
               <p>Manuscript G offers more than eighty emendations in its own <!-- contextu -->.
                  With two or three exceptions where you can recognize another hand, they are the
                  work of the original copyist. Sometimes, he restored verses or words that had been
                  omitted, but for the most part he corrected the more trivial scribal errors. All
                  of the corrections are good, and they are derived from the archetype itself (as
                  agreement with its twin manuscript shows), with only three exceptions: N. 2.73,
                  3.63, 4.10, which the scribe unsucessfully tried to emend. N. 3.53 does not count,
                  since in this passage either the copyist of manuscript N could read poorly, or G
                  entered a correction made either above the line or in the margin of the archetype.
                  But aside from these emendations I found nearly alternate readings in the margine
                  of this manuscript, which most often were added by the copyist himself. All are
                  derived either from some manuscript of no special repute or from the conjecture of
                  some lscholar. For the most part, they are not even worthy of mention.</p>
               <p>If I have done my job, it is clear what we should think about each of these
                  manuscripts. Manuscripts N and G outstrip the others not only in the good quality
                  of their archetype, but also because their copyists were content to transcribe the
                  archetype faithfully, and they generally abstained from interpolating the words of
                  the poets. For very rarely have the words handed down from antiquity been
                  corrupted by the judgment of the scribes. That is why this is the biggest
                  difference between the Neapolitanus and the Gaddianus: that the latter generally
                  <!-- temptavit --> the writing of the archetype by his own devices, but the former
                  admitted the interpolations of inferior manuscripts. And, if we want to think
                  clearly, the Neapolitanus should be preferred in a certain way, but not as Schenkl
                  wanted. For the Gaddianus has nearly the same number of good readings as the
                  Neapolitanus, and sometimes it alone out of all of the manuscripts preserves the
                  genuine reading for us. And so, there is need for both manuscripts in representing
                  the true picture of the archetype.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p>Some text here.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
