<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Bucolica: A Translation</title>
            <author>Calpurnius Siculus</author>
            <editor>samuel J. Huskey</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p><ptr target="http://digitallatin.github.io/viewer/editio-2.0.html"/><ptr
                  target="https://github.com/DigitalLatin/viewer"/></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="translation">
            <div type="textpart" n="1" xml:id="poemtrans1">
               <head>Poem 1. [Corydon, Ornytus]</head>
               <list type="speakers">
                  <item xml:id="Corydon">Corydon</item>
                  <item xml:id="Ornytus">Ornytus</item>
               </list>
               <sp who="#Corydon">
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>The waning summer is not yet taming the sun’s horses, although wine presses
                     squeeze juicy bunches of grapes, and the fermenting grape juice foams with a
                     gentle whisper. Look, Ornytus! Do you see how the cattle that my father
                     entrusted to my care (5) have calmly spread out their flanks under the leafy
                     Spanish broom? Why don’t we also go under the nearby shade? Why are we
                     protecting our parched faces with just a hat?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp who="#Ornytus">
                  <speaker>O.</speaker>
                  <p>Brother Corydon, let’s seek this wood instead, these grottoes of father Faunus;
                     where the pine forest grows lush with slender (10) leaves and raises its head
                     to meet the swift sun, where the beech tree covers the waters bubbling under
                     its base and entwines the shadows with its shifting branches.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp who="#Corydon">
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>I follow wherever you call me, Ornytus. For my Leuce, as long as she denies me
                     her embraces and delight by night, (15) makes the shrines of horned Faunus
                     passable. So, take out your reed pipes and anything you keep hidden; my
                     shepherd’s pipe, which learned Ladon recently built from mature reed, will not
                     fail you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp who="#Ornytus">
                  <speaker>O.</speaker>
                  <p>And now we have come together to the desired shade. (20) But what is this page
                     copied on the sacred beech, which someone recently marked with a hurried blade?
                     Do you see how even now the letter preserves the green cracks and does not yet
                     loosen from the drying wound?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp who="#Corydon">
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>Ornytus, bring your eyes closer: you can quickly run through (25) the verses
                     copied deep in the bark; for your big father gave you long enough limbs, and
                     your generous mother gave you a tall body.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp who="#Ornytus">
                  <speaker>O.</speaker>
                  <p>No shepherd, no traveler sang these lines in some common way, but in fact a god
                     did it. It doesn’t have a bucolic sound, (30) and mountain shepherds’ songs do
                     not adorn the sacred verses.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp who="#Corydon">
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>You’re speaking wonders; but don’t delay, and with careful eye read the divine
                     song to me as soon as possible.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp who="#Ornytus">
                  <speaker>O.</speaker>
                  <p><quote>“I, who watch over mountain ridges and forests, Faunus, spawn of the
                        upper air, I sing to the people the following things that will come to pass:
                        it pleases me (35) to inscribe on this sacred tree cheerful songs to reveal
                        things that are destined. Rejoice above all, you inhabitants of the woods,
                        You, my people, rejoice: the whole flock may roam while its guardian is
                        untroubled, and the shepherd may not wish to close the manger at night with
                        ashen wicker-work, (40) nevertheless the predator does not lay any traps for
                        the sheep or loosen the halters and drive away the mules. A carefree,
                        peaceful golden age is born again. Now that squalor and neglect have been
                        removed, nourishing Themis returns at last to the earth (45) and blessed
                        ages follow the youth who won the case for his maternal Juliae. While the
                        god himself rules over the peoples, wicked Bellona will surrender her hands
                        bound behind her back and, disarmed, she will turn her mad bites against her
                        own innards, and she will wage with herself the civil wars (50) that she
                        spread over the whole world. Now Rome will not mourn any Philippi and will
                        march as a captive at the head of no triumphs. All wars will be brought
                        under a Tartarean prison; they will plunge their heads in shadows and fear
                        the light. Shining peace will appear, shining not only in her face, (55)
                        such as she often was, who was free from open war and far from the conquered
                        foe, yet when arms were on the march routed public discord with her silent
                        sword: Clemency ordered every defect of counterfeit peace to withdraw and
                        pounded to pieces those mad swords. (60) No funereal procession of a senate
                        in chains will exhaust the work of the executioners, and an unfortunate
                        senate house will not count few senators because the jail is full of them.
                        There will be a full peace that, unknowing of the drawn sword, will bring
                        back to Latium another reign of Saturn, (65) another reign of Numa, who
                        first taught the work of peace to the ranks rejoicing in slaughter and still
                        eager for Romulus’ camp and, when he had silenced the weapons, ordered horns
                        to sound among sacred rights, not wars. Now the consul will not purchase the
                        appearance of spurious honor (70) nor silently receive useless fasces or a
                        meaningless seat of office; but once the laws have been returned every right
                        will be present, and a better god will restore the tradition and previous
                        appearance of the forum, and sweep away the ruined age. Let each nation
                        rejoice, whether it inhabits the region lying to the deepest south (75) or
                        the highest north, whether it lies to the east or to the west or boils under
                        the middle of the sky. Do you see how the twentieth night now shines in the
                        clear sky and brings forth a comet beaming with peaceful light? How clearly
                        the star shines without blemish? (80) Can it be that its light does not
                        spatter either pole with blood-red fire, as it usually does, and spark with
                        fiery blood? But once it was not this way, when Caesar was taken away and it
                        announced deadly arms for our poor citizens. Certainly, a god himself will
                        remove the unshaken weight (85) of Roman burden with his strong arms in such
                        a way that the noise of a world handed over will not thunder with a sound
                        and Rome will not think that her dead are rightly deified except when the
                        rising ruler looks back on those who have set before.”</quote></p>
               </sp>
               <sp who="#Corydon">
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>Ornytus, long before now terror mixed with joy has stolen over me (90) and
                     shaken me as though I were full of divine spirit. But let us revere the good
                     spirit of fertile Faunus.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp who="#Ornytus">
                  <speaker>O.</speaker>
                  <p>The songs that the god himself gave us to sing let us sing, and let us play a
                     tune on the tapering reed pipe. Maybe Meliboeus will bring them to august
                     ears.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="2" xml:id="poemtrans2">
               <head>Poem 2. [Idas, Astacus, Thyrsis]</head>
               <list type="speakers">
                  <item xml:id="Idas">Idas</item>
                  <item xml:id="Astacus">Astacus</item>
                  <item xml:id="Thyrsis">Thrysis</item>
               </list>
               <p>Two boys, Astacus, owner of a wooly herd, and Idas, owner of a garden, had long
                  been in love with the virgin Crocale. Both boys were handsome and not unequal in
                  singing. When the opporessive summer heat burns the land, they chance to meet (5)
                  at cool spring under the same shade, and at once they prepare to compete in sweet
                  song, with wagers. Agreed: Idas will surrender seven skins; Astacus, if defeated,
                  will not lay claim to his garden's harvest. The great contest was under the
                  supervision of Thyrsis.</p>
               <p>(10) Every kind of flock was there, every kind of wild beast, and anything that
                  beats the air aloft with roving wings. Under the shady oak there assembled all who
                  were lazily pasturing their sheep, and father Faunus and satyrs with two horns.
                  Dryads were there with dry feet, Naiads with wet feet, (15) and the speeding
                  rivers slowed their pace. The east winds stopped rustling the trembling leaves,
                  and they made a profound silence across all the hills. Everything stopped. Bulls
                  ignored the pasture and tamped it down under their feet. As the two competed, (20)
                  even the worker bees dared to pause from their nectar-sweet flowers.</p>
               <p>And now Thyris took his seat between them under the shade of an ancient tree and
                  said "Boys, if I'm the judge, I suggest that all bets are off. Consider this
                  enough of a prize: the winner gets the praise, and the loser gets the blame. (25)
                  And now, so that you can better distinguish your the verses you trade, raise your
                  hands three times in rapid succession. There's no delay—they decide by count of
                  fingers, and Idas goes first.</p>
               <sp who="#Idas">
                  <speaker>I.</speaker>
                  <p>Slivanus loves me. He gives me responsive reed pipes and surrounds my brows
                     with green pine. (30) When I was still young he declared to me an oracle of no
                     small importance: "Already a slender pipe grows for you on the slanting
                     reed."</p>
               </sp>
               <sp who="#Astacus">
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>Flora adorns her hair for me with pale-green grass, and ripe Pomona plays for
                     me under a tree. The nymphs said "Young man, take possession of these springs,
                     take them. (35) Now you can tend your gardens, well watered by their channeled
                     streams.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp who="#Idas">
                  <speaker>I.</speaker>
                  <p>Pales herself teaches me about caring for the flock, how the black mate of a
                     white ewe changes the fleece on a new-born lamb, which cannot keep the
                     appearance of its different parents, but bears witness to both with its varying
                     color.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp who="#Astacus">
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>(40) Thanks to my skill, no less changeable is the tree that puts on strange
                     leaves and fruit that it has not created. My skill blends a pear with an apple,
                     and it causes grafted peaches to come on gradually alongside unripened
                     plums.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp who="#Idas">
                  <speaker>I.</speaker>
                  <p>It makes me happy to think about carrying tender willow or wild olive tree
                     branches (45) to the young flock, so that they will learn how to graze on the
                     leaves and prune the grass with their young teeth, and so that when they have
                     been weaned, the young will not keep looking for their roaming mothers.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp who="#Astacus">
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>But when I set uprooted plants in the dry soil, the ground is flooded with the
                     overflowing spring and (50) nourished with water, so that the weak cuttings do
                     not seek their former sap in the dirt where they have been transplanted.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp who="#Idas">
                  <speaker>I.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, if only some god would bring Crocale here! I will say that he is master of
                     the the earth, that he alone is master of the heavens. I will declare the wood
                     his, and I will say, "A spirit lives under this tree. (55) Go far away, you
                     uninitiated ones! Go! This place is holy!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp who="#Astacus">
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>I burn for Crocale. If any of the gods hears my prayers, a beechen ___ will be
                     offered to him alone among the vine-covered elms, where the glittering spring
                     carries its fresh waters and courses by the lilies with its babbling
                     stream.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp who="#Idas">
                  <speaker>I.</speaker>
                  <p>(60) Don't look down on my cottage and rustic shelter: Idas is a country boy, I
                     reckon, but he's not uncultivated. Often a lamb trembles on my kindled altar;
                     often a ewe lamb is solemnly dedicated and sacrificed in celebration of the
                     Parilia</p>
               </sp>
               <sp who="#Astacus">
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>It is my custom to send the first fruits to the protecting gods of my fruitful
                     garden (65) and to hang sacrificial cakes on Priapus. I also offer dripping
                     honeycombs and flowing honey. And these things are no less pleasing than if a
                     goat were to spill his blood on my altar.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp who="#Idas">
                  <speaker>I.</speaker>
                  <p>I feed a thousand bleating lambs on their mothers' udders, and just as many
                     Tarentine ewes produce fleecefor me. (70) Snow-white cheese is pressed all year
                     long for me. If you come to me, Crocale, the whole year will serve you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp who="#Astacus">
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>If someone should want to count how many apples I pick beneath my trees, he
                     will count the fine sands more quickly. We always have a harvest of vegetables,
                     and neither winter nor summer hampers our work. (75) If you come, Crocale, the
                     whole harvest will serve you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp who="#Idas">
                  <speaker>I.</speaker>
                  <p>Though the dry field parches our wilting grasses, take the milk pail full of
                     sloshing milk. We'll offer their fleece when the sunny weather comes on, and
                     the shearing will happen on the warm Kalends.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp who="#Astacus">
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>(80) But we, whom even the scorching summer rewards, will give you a thousand
                     Chian figs with shining skins, and just as many chestnuts, when their green
                     husks are burst by ripe nuts under the December sun.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp who="#Idas">
                  <speaker>I.</speaker>
                  <p>But you don't think I'm ugly, do you? And burdened with years? (85) Am I a sad
                     sack, kidding myself whenever I touch my hand to my tender face and follow the
                     traces of my youthful prime, or do I unwittingly trick my fingers with the fine
                     down of youth?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp who="#Astacus">
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>Whenever I catch sight of myself in clear springs, I'm surprised, since (90) my
                     face is covered with the flower of youth just like I have often noticed waxy
                     quinces on their tree, glistening under their delicate fuzz.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp who="#Idas">
                  <speaker>I.</speaker>
                  <p>Love demands poetry, and shepherd's pipe doesn't shy away from the theme of
                     love. But look! The day flees and evening revives the twilight. You, Daphnis,
                     drive the flock on this side, and Alphesiboeus on that side.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp who="#Astacus">
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>(95) Now the leaves stir and the tree rustles over our songs: Go from her,
                     Dorylas! Go! Close off the full chanel and allow it to water my gardens that
                     have been thirsty all this while.</p>
               </sp>
               <p>Barely had they finished, when old Thyrsis said, "It's a tie! And so live in
                  harmony, (100) for good looks, song, love, and age unite you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="3" xml:id="poemtrans3">
               <head>Poem 3. [Iollas, Lycidas]</head>
               <list type="speakers">
                  <item xml:id="Iollas">Iollas</item>
                  <item xml:id="Lycidas">Lycidas</item>
               </list>
               <sp who="#Iollas">
                  <speaker>I.</speaker>
                  <p>Lycidas, by any chance have you see my heifer in this valley? She usually meets
                     with your bulls, and now the search has taken nearly two hours. She hasn't been
                     found, and (5) I haven't hesitated to ruin my legs by slicing them to pieces on
                     these hard thorns and brambles. I haven't accomplished anything after so much
                     bloodshed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp who="#Lycidas">
                  <speaker>L.</speaker>
                  <p>I haven't been paying enough attention: I don't have the time. I burn, Iollas.
                     I burn uncontrollably: that ungrateful Phyllis has left her Lycidas, and after
                     all of my gifts she loves young Mopsus.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp who="#Iollas">
                  <speaker>I.</speaker>
                  <p>(10) Woman! More shifting than the winds! That's your Phyllis. As I recall,
                     whenever you were away by yourself, she used to swear that even honey seemed
                     bitter to her without you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp who="#Lycidas">
                  <speaker>L.</speaker>
                  <p>If you have the time, I'll launch into more detailed complaints, Iollas. Make
                     for those willows and turn under the elms on the left. (15) When it's hot in the
                     meadows, my bull likes to rest there. He stretches out in the cool shade and
                     regurgitates the grass he ate in the morning.</p>
               </sp>


            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
